A Guide to the American Conservation Association (ACA) records FA475
Rockefeller Archive Center
American Conservation Association (ACA) records
1958-2010
Rockefeller Archive Center
American Conservation Association
FA475
206.98 Cubic Feet
158 standard record storage boxes.
Related Archival Materials note
Jackson Hole Preserve, Inc. records Laurance S. Rockefeller papers
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 15 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical/Historical note
Established in 1958 by Jackson Hole Preserve Inc., the American Conservation Association (ACA) was designed to carry on the educational, research, and citizen action activities that the Preserve felt was beyond its own capabilities. The ACA has supplied vital finances and leadership for initiatives to protect the park, refuge, forest, and recreation resources in this country. ACA's efforts to educate the public and secure its support have often been seminal to the establishment of important environmental and conservation organizations.
Scope and Contents note
The collection primarily consists of grant files, administrative records and financial records.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as received by Rockefeller Archive Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
American Conservation Association deposited the records at the Rockefeller Archive Center in April 1985.
RAC began receiving ACA records in 1990 (Accession 1990:117). Additions and accruals to the collection have been received in multiple accessions, and continue periodically as applicable.
- Grant Files, 1
  - Grant Files, 1964-1971; 1.1
    - American Conservation - A (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - B (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - Bodinson, Holt (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - C (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - D-E (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - F-G (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - H-J (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - K-L (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - M (Box 1)
    - American Conservation - N (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - O-P (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - Q-R (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - S (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - T (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - Ua-United (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - University-Uz (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - V (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - W-We (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - Wing, William G. (Box 2)
    - American Conservation - Wh-XYZ (Box 2)
    - Adirondack Mountain National Park (Proposed) (Box 3)
    - Alaska (State of) Recreation and Tourist Potential Plan (Box 3)
    - American Camping Association (Box 3)
    - American Fisheries Society (Box 3)
    - American Forestry Association (Box 3)
    - American Hotel and Motel Association (Box 3)
    - American Institute of Park Executives (Book on Parks Admin.), 2 folders. (Box 3)
    - American Littoral Society (Box 3)
    - American Pioneer Trails Association, Inc. (Box 3)
    - American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society (Box 3)
    - American Shore and Beach Preservation Association (Box 3)
    - American Society of Landscape Architects (and Foundation) (Box 3)
    - American Youth Hostels, Inc. (Box 3)
    - Applicants A-Z (Box 3)
    - Belle W. Baruch Foundation (Box 3)
    - Bevans, Michael H. (Box 3)
    - Bowdoin College (Box 3)
    - Brunstead, Dr. Harlan (Box 3)
    - Camp Fire Girls Inc. (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association, 3 folders. (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association - Caribbean Study (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association - Caribbean Study - Caribbean Conference (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association - Caribbean Study - Caribbean Conference - Printed Material (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association - Caribbean Study - Caribbean Organization (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association - Caribbean Study - Carl A. Carlozzi Loan to Trinidad (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association - Caribbean Study - Finances (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association - Caribbean Study - Trip (Box 3)
    - College of the Virgin Islands - Dr. Carl A Carlozzi Projects (Box 4)
    - Central American (Dry Zone) Guatemala - Costa Rica (Box 5)
    - Chamber of Commerce - Small Business Chamber of Commerce of New York City - Lenox Avenue East Beautification (Box 5)
    - Citizen's Committee for Clean Water, 2 folders. (Box 5)
    - Citizen's Union Research Foundation, Inc. (Box 5)
    - Cluster Development - General, 2 folders. (Box 5)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes subfolders of Clippings, and Inventory Sales.
    - Cluster Development - William H. Whyte (Box 5)
    - Cluster Development - William H. Whyte - Distribution (Box 5)
    - College of Virgin Islands (Box 5)
    - College of Virgin Islands - Caribbean Conservation Association Grant (Box 5)
    - College of Virgin Islands - Printed Material, 2 folders. (Box 6)
    - Colorado Open Space Foundation (Box 6)
    - Committee for Environmental Information (Box 6)
    - Committee for Environmental Information - Printed Material (Box 6)
      Formerly "Scientists and Citizen"
    - Committee for Nuclear Information (Box 6)
    - Community Council of Greater New York - High Rock Park, Staten Island (Box 6)
    - Concern, Inc. (Box 6)
    - Conference of State Inter-Agency Committee on Recreation (Box 6)
    - Conservation Foundation, 3 folders. (Box 6)
    - Conservation Foundation - Alaska Research Center (Box 6)
    - Conservation Foundation - Printed Material (Box 6)
    - Conservation Foundation - Consolidation (Box 7)
    - Conservation Foundation - Consolidation - Vogt- Latin American Study and Meeting (Box 7)
    - Conservation Center in Denver (Box 7)
    - Conservation Law Society of America (Box 7)
    - Conservation Library Center, 1967 (Box 7)
    - Conservation Library Center, 1964 (Box 7)
    - Conservation Library Center - Denver, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Conservation Library Center - Denver, 1959-1962 (Box 7)
    - Conservation Society of Southern Vermont (Box 7)
    - Contributions - Individuals - A-N (Box 7)
    - Contributions - Individuals - O-Z (Box 7)
    - Council of State Governments (Box 7)
    - J.N. "Ding"Darling Foundation, Inc. (Lewis and Clark Trail) (Box 7)
    - Dartmouth College ("A Return Danube Expedition") (Box 7)
    - Diamond, Henry L. - General Correspondence - A-F (Box 8)
    - Diamond, Henry L. - General Correspondence - G-M (Box 8)
    - Diamond, Henry L. - General Correspondence - N-S (Box 8)
    - Diamond, Henry L. - General Correspondence - T-Z (Box 8)
    - Diamond, Henry L. - Memos, etc. (Box 8)
    - Diamond, Henry L. - Clippings (Box 8)
    - Diamond, Henry L. - Red Cross Article Memos/ Invitations (Box 8)
    - Henry L. Diamond - Mineral King Development Company (Box 8)
    - Henry L. Diamond - Mineral King Development Company - Proposal Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Henry L. Diamond - Speeches - A-F (Box 8)
    - Henry L. Diamond - Speeches - G-R (Box 8)
    - Henry L. Diamond - Speeches - S-Z (Box 8)
    - Henry L. Diamond - Travel (Box 8)
    - Educational Facilities Laboratories, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Elm Research Institute (Box 9)
    - Environmental Defense Fund (Box 9)
    - Environmental Teach- In, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Environmental Television Institute (Box 9)
    - Federal Legislative Bill "Federal Open Space and Urban Development Act of 1961" (Box 9)
    - Federated Conservationists of Westchester County (Box 9)
    - Fishes of the West Indies (Proposed Book) (Box 9)
    - Five Year Program (Box 9)
    - Forer, Mrs. Lois G. (Box 9)
    - Forest History Society, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Foresta Institute for Ocean and Mountain Studies (Box 9)
    - Foundation of America (Box 9)
    - Foundation of America - Articles of Incorporation and By- Laws (Box 9)
    - Girl Scouts of the USA (Box 9)
    - Greer Children's Community (Box 9)
    - Gregg, Frank (Box 9)
    - Harlem River/ New York University (Box 9)
    - Harlem River/New York University - Printed Material (Box 9)
    - Historical Society of Martinique (Box 10)
    - Institute of Man and Science (Box 10)
    - Institute of Northern Agricultural Research (Box 10)
    - International Committee on National Parks - General Correspondence (Box 10)
    - International Committee of National Parks - Budget (Box 10)
    - International Committee of National Parks - Congo Park (Box 10)
    - International Committee on National Parks - Printed Material (Box 10)
    - International Union for Conservation of Nature and Resources (IUCN), 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Jackson Hole Preserve, Inc. - Gift to ACA (Box 11)
    - Lyndon B. Johnson Book (Box 11)
      Includes a subfolder: Lyndon B. Johnson Book - People Requesting Commercial Edition
    - Lake Champlain Committee (Box 11)
    - Lamb, George R. (Box 11)
    - Lamb, George R. - Keep Rye Beautiful (Box 11)
    - Lamb, George R. - Troy Meadows, 2 folders. (Box 11)
    - League of Women Voters Educational Fund (Box 11)
    - Manomet Bird Observatory (Box 11)
    - Marincello Project, California (Box 11)
    - Marine Research Foundation (Box 11)
    - Marine Research Foundation - Carl O. Gustafson/Shellfish Culture Study (Box 11)
    - Mariposa County (Box 11)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) (Box 11)
    - Morgan, A. K. - Trip for ACA - Interstate Park at Lake Tahoe (Box 12)
    - National Academy of Sciences (Box 12)
    - National Audubon Society (Box 12)
    - National Capital Planning Commission (Box 12)
    - National Conference on Outdoor Recreation (Box 12)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs, 2 folders. (Box 12)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs - Material Used (Box 12)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs - Reservations (Box 12)
    - National Planning Association (Box 12)
    - National Recreation Association - Contributions (Box 12)
    - National Recreation and Park Association (Box 12)
    - National Roadside Council (Proposed) (Box 12)
    - National Youth Conference on Natural Beauty and Conservation (Box 12)
    - National Youth Conference on Natural Beauty and Conservation - Printed Material (Box 12)
    - Natural Area Council (Box 12)
    - Natural History Society - Wolf Springs Forest (Box 13)
    - Natural Resources Council of America (Box 13)
    - Natural Resources Defense Council, Inc. (Box 13)
    - Nature Conservancy (Box 13)
    - Nature Conservancy - Printed Material (Box 13)
    - New England Forestry Foundation (Box 13)
    - New York City - Park Planning (Box 13)
    - New York State - Governor's Conference on Natural Beauty (Box 13)
    - New York State - Conservation Department- Booz, Allen, & Hamilton Study (Box 13)
    - New York State - Historic Trust (Box 13)
    - New York State - Natural Heritage Trust (Box 13)
    - Recreation Council Advisory Committee (Box 13)
    - Temporary Study Commission on the Future of the Adirondacks (Box 13)
    - Palisades Interstate Park Commission - Hudson River Valley Commission (Box 15)
    - Palisades Interstate Park Commission - Iona Island Study (Box 15)
    - Pan American Development Foundation, Inc. (Vicuna Reserve) (Box 15)
    - Park Association of New York City, Inc. (Box 15)
    - Park Facilities (Box 15)
    - Philadelphia Conservationists, Inc. (Box 15)
    - Prospect Park (Centennial Committee) (Box 15)
    - Public Affairs Committee, Inc. (Box 15)
    - Rockefeller, Steven C. (Box 16)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Restricted from scholarly research. Records which document the activities of living members of the Rockefeller family are restricted.
    - Save the Redwoods League (Box 16)
    - Save the Redwoods League - Kenneth Chorley Trip (Box 16)
    - Save the Redwoods League - Printed Material (Box 16)
    - Save the Redwoods League - Rockefeller Redwood Forest (Box 16)
    - Setzer, Gene W., materials (Box 16)
    - Sierra Club (Box 16)
    - Smith, Frederick (Box 16)
    - Smith, Frederick - Addresses (Box 16)
    - Smithsonian Institute - International Council for Bird Protection (Box 16)
    - Sport Fishery Research Foundation (Box 16)
    - State Council of Parks (Box 16)
    - State Council of Parks - Forest Preserve Booklet (Box 16)
    - State Council of Parks and Recreation (Box 16)
    - State University of New York - Horticulture Book (Box 16)
    - Student Conservation (Box 16)
    - Student Conservation Association, Inc. - General Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 16)
    - Student Conservation Program, 1962-1964 (Box 16)
    - Student Conservation Program, 1960-1961 (Box 16)
    - Student Conservation Program, 1956-1959 (Box 17)
    - Student Conservation Association - Meetings/Minutes (Box 17)
    - Student Conservation Association - Printed Material (Box 17)
    - Student Conservation Association - Releases (Box 17)
    - Sunken Forest Preserve, Inc. (Box 17)
    - Sylvania Tract, Ottawa National Forest (Box 17)
    - Thorne Ecological Foundation (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of Agriculture - Forest Service (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of the Interior (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of the Interior - Bureau of Outdoor Recreation (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of Interior - Fish and Wildlife Service - Bureau of Sport Fisheries and Wildlife (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of Interior - National Park Service (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of Interior - National Park Service - Allagash River National Recreation Area in Maine (Publications) (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of Interior - National Park Service - Book - "The National Park Service Manager of Land for People" (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of Interior - National Park Service - Hawaii (Study) (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of Interior - National Park Service - Prairie National Park in Kansas (Publications) (Box 17)
    - United States Government - Department of Interior - National Park Service - Yellowstone National Park - 100th Anniversary Film (Box 17)
    - Citizen's Advisory Committee on Recreation and Natural Beauty - Joint Task Force on the Environment of the Electric Utility Industry (Box 17)
    - University of Michigan (Box 17)
    - University of Wisconsin - Fox Irving - Water Resources Center Study, 2 folders. (Box 18)
    - Vermont - Ottaquechee Project, 2 folders. (Box 18)
    - Vermont - Projects (Box 18)
    - Vollmer Associates - Parking Study (Box 18)
    - WGBH Educational Foundation (Box 18)
    - William C. Walker Sons, Inc. (Box 19)
    - lzaak Walton League of America (Box 19)
    - White House Conference on Natural Beauty (Box 19)
    - Whyte, William H. (Box 19)
    - Wildlife Management Institute (Box 19)
    - Wildlife Society (Box 19)
    - Wirth, Conrad L. (Box 19)
    - Woodside, California - AEC Situation (Box 19)
    - Woodside, California - AEC Situation - Printed Material (Box 19)
    - Yeomans, W.C. (Box 19)
    - Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. (YWCA) (Box 19)
    - Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. (YWCA) - Manual "Community Action for Outdoor Recreation and Conservation" (Box 19)
    - Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. (YWCA) - Material Distributed at YMCS Conference (Box 19)
    - Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. (YWCA) - National Board Conference at Jackson Hole, 1966 July (Box 19)
    - Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. (YWCA) - National Board Conference at Jackson Hole, 1964 July (Box 19)
    - Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. (YWCA) - Printed Material (Box 19)
    - William H. Whyte Manuscript 1967 Revision "The Lost Landscape", 2 folders. (Box 20)
  - Grant Files, 1972-1981; 1.2
    - A-Co (Box 21)
    - Co-Gz (Box 22)
    - H-N (Box 23)
    - Ni-R (Box 24)
    - S-University C (Box 25)
    - University D-Z (Box 26)
    - Adirondack Council (Box 27)
    - Alaskan Conservation Foundation (Box 27)
    - American Association of State and Local History (Box 27)
    - American Farmland Trust (Box 27)
    - American Land Forum (Box 27)
    - American Littoral Society, 2 folders. (Box 27)
    - American Society of Landscape Architects Foundation (Box 27)
    - American Society of Landscape Architects Foundation (Box 27)
    - Annual Report (Box 27)
    - Applicants - A-E (Box 27)
      Restricted from scholarly access - personnel material.
    - Applicants - A-F (Box 27)
    - Applicants - F-M (Box 27)
    - Applicants - G-M (Box 27)
    - Applicants - N-R (Box 27)
    - Applicants - N-Z (Box 27)
    - Applicants - S-Z (Box 27)
    - Board of Trustees (Box 27)
    - By- Laws, 2 folders. (Box 28)
    - Caribbean Conservation Association, 2 folders. (Box 28)
    - Catskills Project (Box 28)
    - Center for the Hudson River Valley (Box 28)
    - Chesapeake Bay Foundation (Box 28)
    - Citizen's Advisory Committee on Environmental Quality, 2 folders. (Box 28)
    - Citizen's Committee for New York City (Box 28)
    - Clippings (Box 28)
    - Cluster Development, 2 folders. (Box 28)
    - Coast Alliance (Box 28)
    - College of the Virgin Islands, 2 folders. (Box 28)
    - Concern, 2 folders. (Box 28)
    - Conservation Foundation, 4 folders. (Box 28)
    - Conservation Foundation - Clippings (Box 28)
    - Conservation Foundation - Printed Material (Box 28)
    - Consultants, Harry Rand, 2 folders. (Box 29)
    - Contributions (Box 29)
    - Coral Reef Society, Inc. (Box 29)
    - Cornell University - Lab of Ornithology (Box 29)
    - Couch-Sa-Chra-Ga Association, Inc. (Box 29)
    - Council on Environmental Alternations (Box 29)
    - Educational Facilities Laboratories (Box 29)
    - Elm Research Institute (Box 29)
    - Environmental Defense Fund (Box 29)
    - Environmental Law Institute (Box 29)
    - Environmental Priorities - Meetings/Minutes, 2 folders. (Box 29)
    - Environmental Priorities - Reports (Box 29)
    - Federated Conservationists of Westchester County (Box 29)
    - Film Material, 2 folders. (Box 29)
    - Finances, 2 folders. (Box 29)
    - Finances/Gifts to ACA (Box 29)
    - Forest History Society (Box 30)
    - Fresh Air Fund (Box 30)
    - Friends of the Earth Foundation (Box 30)
    - Greenfield, New York (Box 30)
    - Helm Shapiro Ayers & Aldrich, P.C. (Box 30)
    - Human Environment Center (Box 30)
    - Incorporation By-Laws (Box 30)
    - Inform (Box 30)
    - Insurance (Box 30)
    - Island Resources Foundation (Box 30)
    - Island Resources Foundation - "Foxfire" Project (Box 30)
    - LBJ Memorial Grove on the Potomac - Society for a More Beautiful National Capital, Inc., 2 folders. (Box 30)
    - Lamb, George R., 2 folders. (Box 30)
    - Legal (Box 30)
    - "Man & His Urban Environment" (Box 30)
    - Manomet Bird Observatory (Box 30)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 2 folders. (Box 30)
    - Memorandum (Box 30)
    - Merger (Box 30)
    - Meetings/Minutes - Annual, 1976-1981; 10 folders. (Box 30)
    - Meetings/Minutes, 1972-1975; 8 folders. (Box 31)
    - John Muir Institute for Environmental Studies, Inc., 2 folders. (Box 31)
    - Municipal Art Society of New York (Box 31)
    - National Academy of Sciences, 2 folders. (Box 31)
    - National Audubon Society (Box 31)
    - National Maritime Historical Society (Box 31)
    - National Parks and Conservation Association, 2 folders. (Box 31)
    - National Recreation and Parks Association - Citizens Advisory Committee on Environmental Quality, 2 folders. (Box 31)
    - Natural Area Council, 2 folders. (Box 31)
    - Natural Beauty Commission, 2 folders. (Box 31)
    - Natural Resources Council of America (Box 31)
    - Natural Resources Defense Council, 2 folders. (Box 31)
    - Natural Resources Defense Council, 3 folders. (Box 32)
    - Nature Conservancy, 2 folders. (Box 32)
    - New York Conservation Council & American Game Association FDN (Box 32)
    - N.Y. City - Council on the Environment of New York City (Box 32)
    - N.Y. State - Adirondack Park Agency (Box 32)
    - N.Y. State - Natural Heritage Trust (Box 32)
    - New York-New Jersey Trail Conference (Box 32)
    - NY State - Department of Environmental Conservation (Box 32)
    - Office Space, 2 folders. (Box 32)
    - Organization, 2 folders. (Box 32)
    - Palisades Interstate Park Commission (Box 32)
    - Park Council, 2 folders. (Box 32)
    - Printed Matter (Box 32)
    - Project for Public Spaces (Box 32)
    - Public Lands Institute (Box 32)
    - Quebec Labrador Foundation - Atlantic Center for the Environment (Box 32)
    - Rocky Mountain Center on Environment (Box 32)
    - Save the Redwoods League, 2 folders. (Box 32)
    - Scientists Institute for Public Information (Environmental Magazine) (Box 32)
    - Sierra Club, 2 folders. (Box 32)
    - Smithsonian Institution International Council for Bird Preservation (Box 33)
    - State Communities Aid Association (Box 33)
    - Student Conservation Association (Box 33)
    - Subscriptions, 2 folders. (Box 33)
    - Taxes, 2 folders. (Box 33)
      Restricted from scholarly access - financial material.
    - Taxes, Federal, 2 folders. (Box 33)
    - Trustees for Alaska (Box 33)
    - U.S. Government - American Revolution Bicentennial Commission (Box 33)
    - U.S. Government - Department of the Interior- National Park Service (Box 33)
    - U.S. Government - Natural Heritage Trust (Box 33)
    - U.S. Government - Environmental Protection Agency (Box 33)
    - University of Michigan (Box 33)
    - Urban Environment Foundation (Box 33)
    - Virgin Islands Conservation Society Inc., 2 folders. (Box 33)
    - Wave Hill Center for Environmental Studies, 2 folders. (Box 33)
    - Whyte, William H., 2 folders. (Box 33)
    - Wilderness Society, 2 folders. (Box 33)
    - Wildlife Management Institute (Box 33)
    - Wildlife-Wildland Institute (Box 34)
    - World Wildlife Fund U.S. (Box 34)
    - Forest History Society Inc. (Box 34)
    - Fresh Air Fund (Box 34)
    - Helm, Shapiro Ayers & Aldrich P.C. (Box 34)
    - By-Laws Incorporation (Box 34)
    - Inform (Box 34)
    - Institute of Northern Agricultural Research (Box 34)
    - Insurance (Box 34)
    - International Union for Conservation of Nature & Natural Resources (Box 34)
    - Island Resources Foundation, 3 folders. (Box 34)
  - Grant Files, 1982-1986; 1.3
    - American Conservation Association, A-Z (Box 60)
    - Adirondack Land Trust Inc. (Box 60)
    - American Land Forum (Box 60)
    - American Land Rescue Association (Box 60)
    - American Rivers Conservation Council Contributions (Box 60)
    - Appalachian Mountain Club (Box 60)
    - Bank Street College of Education (Box 61)
    - Board of Trustees (Box 61)
    - The Catskill Center for Conservation and Development (Box 61)
    - Center for Negotiation and Public Policy Inc. (Box 61)
    - Central Park Conservancy (Box 61)
    - Clean Water Fund (Box 61)
    - Coalition for Scenic Beauty (Box 61)
    - Coast Alliance (Box 61)
    - Conservation Foundation (Box 61)
    - Duke University (Box 61)
    - Enviromnental Defense Fund Inc. (Box 61)
    - Enviromnental Law Institute (Box 61)
    - Enviromnental Planning Lobby (EPL Institute Inc.) (Box 61)
    - Enviromnental Policy Institute (Box 61)
    - Federated Conservationists of Westchester County Inc. (Box 61)
    - Federation of New York State Bird Clubs Inc. (Box 61)
    - Finances (Box 61)